孤国春秋：七王必死
（根据伯纳德康威尔原着小说改编）
一百年来，这片土地动荡不安
For a hundred years, there was chaos in our lands.
萨克逊人和丹麦入侵者掀起战争
War between Saxons and Dane invaders.
觊觎王位者大动干戈
And war between men who wanted to be kings.
我追随的乌特雷德大人 乌特雷德之子 由丹麦人养大的萨克逊人
My lord, Uhtred, son of Uhtred, born a Saxon, but raised a Dane,
则带来了片刻的安宁
had brought about a fragile peace.
随着爱德华国王健康恶化
But as King Edward's health faltered,
动乱接踵而来
trouble spread.
尽管多数王国向萨克逊人宣誓效忠
And while most of the country was sworn to the Saxons,
乌特雷德的诺桑比亚却拒绝称臣
Uhtred's land of Northumbria was not.
这也成了敌人亟欲利用的弱点
And enemies were keen to exploit this.
（德文特河）
（西诺桑比亚，德文特河）
狼战士！
Wolf!
Wolf! [grunts] Wolf!
把这里毁了，别让人发现我们上岸
Destroy the settlement. Leave no sign we have landed.
安拉夫，间谍来了
Anlaf, we have the spy.
我的孩子啊
Behold my child.
安拉夫之女
Behold the daughter of Anlaf.
像个小丑
You look ridiculous.
这是他们的装扮，父亲
It is how they dress, Father.
要混入人群就得…
If I'm to hide amongst them, I must appear--
爱德华国王死了吗？
Is King Edward dead?
还没
Not yet.
-但快了 -那我们来对了
-But each breath could be his last. -Then we chose our moment.
国王驾崩后，萨克逊人必然会起内哄
A king dies, Saxons always turn on each other.
去通知所有不满他们的国王
Pass this news to all kings who hate them.
说我已从爱尔兰前来，正在寻求结盟
Tell them I have crossed from Irland and wish to make allies.
你回温彻斯特吧
Return yourself to Winchester.
等待时机
Wait.
好好玩弄他们
Play with them.
制造混乱
Unleash chaos.
（温彻斯特）
（威塞克斯王国，温彻斯特）
别动，退后
No. Stay back.
找出王后！
Find the queen!
艾格芙王后
Lady Eadgifu,
叛徒艾弗维尔 派人来保护你和艾德蒙王子
the traitor Aelfweard has sent men to take you and Prince Edmund into protection.
我拒绝成为人质
I have no wish to be a hostage.
-能击退他们吗？ -除非有艾索斯坦
-Can we fight them? -Not without Aethelstan.
守卫一定能…
Well, surely, my guards can--
人们开始选边站了
Loyalties are shifting and factions forming.
我们不知道谁能信任
It is not certain who supports us.
应该趁早带着王子去避难
We should flee with your son whilst we can.
这简直无法饶恕
I will not forgive this.
我也不会原谅艾索斯坦 让我们陷入险境
Nor forgive Aethelstan for leaving us exposed.
竟然抛下我们
Damn him for his absence.
来吧，艾德蒙，我们要走了
Come, Edmund. We are leaving.
王后呢？动作快！搜！
- Where's the queen? - Move! Look everywhere!
-母后，这是… -别说话
- Mother, what's-- - Sh. Quiet.
等等
-Wait.
皮尔里各
- Pyrlig. - We got word.
艾索斯坦为了祈求父亲平安 踏上朝圣之旅了
Aethelstan has gone on pilgrimage to pray for his father's health.
去找他，告诉他国王死了 然后帮我赏他一巴掌
Then find him and tell him of his death.
他发誓要保护我们的
Then strike him, from me, for he swore to protect us.
来吧，没时间了
Come. There's no time.
你们要去找谁？
Where will you go?
-乌特雷德 -投靠异教徒？
-To Uhtred. -The pagan?
-他们在里面 -快走
- They're in here! - Go! Go!
乌特雷德背叛了我丈夫
Uhtred betrayed my husband.
这样妥吗？
Are we sure this is wise?
乌特雷德视艾索斯坦如己出 绝对可靠
Uhtred was like a father to Aethelstan. He can be trusted.
我们要去最后的王国
We go to the last kingdom.
（贝班堡）
（诺桑比亚王国，贝班堡）
他在军队前大喊：“放箭！”
He stood in front of the army, and he said, "Release the arrows!"
结果一支箭射穿了他的头
And an arrow went right through his head.
真的太精采了
Oh, that was something.
这片土地上的战役将流传千古
But then, the battle for this place certainly sticks in the memory.
-两场都是 -对，肯努特
-Both times. - Hey. Cnut.
他是个好老二
He was a proper… cock!
还有凶猛的屠马人
Then there were the horse-killers. Oh, they were deadly.
-他叫什么？ -血发
-What was his name? -Bloodhair.
血发，女巫又叫什么？
Bloodhair. And what was her name? She of the curses?
别提了，她叫丝凯德
Do not remind me. Skade!
她是疯婆娘
Now, she was moon touched.
另一位先知的下场不太好喔
Another one who thought she was a seer. It didn't go well for her.
那真的是预知梦，我梦到三次了
I am telling you, my dream was a prophecy. Three nights I have had it.
-你梦到什么，英格丽丝？ -别问了，大人
-And what is your dream, Ingrith? - Don't get her started, Lord.
听好了，“七王丧钟”
-Hear my words. "Seven kings must die." - Lord?
-七位国王和… -英格丽丝
-Seven kings and-- -Ingrith!
注意，王后来了
All stand for the queen!
艾格芙王后
Queen Eadgifu.
还有我最尊贵的朋友，艾德汉大人
And my most noble friend, Lord Aldhelm.
什么风把你们吹来了？
What brings you this far north?
我们母子来寻求庇护
I come seeking refuge with my son.
爱德华国王驾崩了
Edward, rightful king of these lands, has died.
我很遗憾
Then my heart grieves.
我一直想要和解
I'd hoped to reconcile.
一个挂了，还剩六个
One down, six to go.
够了，我不喜欢这样
No! I do not like it.
诺桑比亚将承认艾索斯坦为新王
Northumbria recognizes the new king, Aethelstan.
艾索斯坦不一定能即位
Do not assume Aethelstan will be king.
-有谁拥护艾弗维尔？ -威塞克斯诸位郡长
-Who is supporting Aelfweard? - The ealdormen of Wessex.
不意外，还在说艾索斯坦是私生子？
Of course. Still claiming Aethelstan's a bastard?
对，威尔特郡为艾弗维尔提供金援
Yes. Aelfweard has the wealth of Wiltunscir behind him.
我们在艾尔斯伯里的间谍 通报他正在当地公开招兵买马
Our spies in Aegelesburg say he's there, openly recruiting mercenaries.
我们要在他壮大前 去艾尔斯伯里逮住他
We will go to Aegelesburg and seize him before he is at full force.
我们希望你采取防守姿态
We would prefer your guard.
我的提议能争取时间 让艾索斯坦去温彻斯特加冕为王
My offer gives Aethelstan the time to go to Winchester to be crowned,
还能避免军事冲突
and we avoid a clash of armies.
-我立誓要守护艾索斯坦…
I swore an oath to protect Aethelstan--
对，你是信守诺言的人
And of course, you are a man of your word.
但你没有履行向国王称臣的承诺
Yet your oath to swear your lands to the king remains unfulfilled.
你的丈夫对丹麦后裔充满敌意
Your husband showed himself hostile to those of Danish blood.
他不是统一英格兰的最佳人选
As such, he was not the right man to unite England.
否则英格兰早就统一了
If he had been, England would be united.
现在不一样了
But now things can be different.
艾索斯坦可以是 实现萨克逊人梦想的国王
Aethelstan can be the king to fulfill the Saxon dream.
除非他发誓…
If he chooses to swear--
我已宣誓效忠，我的誓言依旧有效
I swore an oath of loyalty, and it stands.
如果艾弗维尔在招募佣兵 一定会到处放话
If Aelfweard is buying mercenaries, he will be looking for men from all parts.
这样还能发动突袭吗？
Do you think we can still execute an ambush?
如果是为了艾索斯坦，当然没问题
If it is for Aethelstan, then yes.
-只要他不睡着 -就那么一次
-If he does not fall asleep. -Once. I fell asleep once.
确定不派年轻战士吗？
Are you certain this is better than a band of young fighters?
我听说你们最近都在饮酒作乐
I hear you do little these days but feast and hunt.
我不会把自己发的誓 丢给年轻人去实现
I will not send young men to do a task I swore to do myself.
来吧，臭家伙…
Come on, you little…
快啊
Come on! Come on.
现在停下来。
Stop it now.
奥斯柏，边境怎么样？ 苏格兰人没作乱吧？
Osbert! What news from our borders? Do the Scots behave themselves?
父亲，听说德文特河畔有狼战士
Yes, Father. There are rumors Wolf-Warriors landed near Derwent.
-狼战士？ -你背着剑做什么？
-Wolf-Warriors? -Why are you carrying your sword?
我们要去保护艾索斯坦 不受他弟弟伤害
We're riding to protect Aethelstan from his brother.
我也去
Then I will come.
- 我要与你并肩作战留下来 - 守着你应得的领土吧
-Any fight of yours is mine. -Stay here and protect your birthright.
被动等待准没好事
No good comes of sitting waiting for a birthright.
那你就训练马匹
So you train the horses
教教那男孩怎么保护自己
and you teach that boy how to defend himself.
先王的三儿子不怎么讨喜
No one likes the third son of a dead king.
父亲
Father.
-你会向艾索斯坦称臣吗？ -我必须遵守诺言
-Will you swear our lands to Aethelstan? -I must honor my word.
诺桑比亚人一定会很舍不得 他们的异教领主
Northumbrians will be sad to lose their pagan lord.
终于出来了
Gotcha!
这个小王八蛋
-Look at this little bastard. -Are we ready?
-准备好了吗？ -他在抱怨他的马鞍
He's complaining about his saddle.
-说害他屁股痛 -不是屁股，是背
-Says his arse gets sore. - Didn't say arse. I said my back.
我帮你做了这个
I made you this.
你们每个人都有
And one for each of you.
坐在冷冰冰的地上 迟早变成冷冰冰的尸体
Men who sit on cold earth find the cold earth calls for them.
她再次证明了自己的预知能力
Once again, she shows herself a seer.
大人，你别当真
Lord, it was nothing.
再说一次吧
Tell it again.
“七王丧钟”，大人
"Seven kings must die," Lord.
-“七位国王…” -别说了
-"Seven kings--" -Ingrith, no.
继续说
Go on.
“和你心爱的女人”
"And the woman you love."
我并非国王，也没有女人
I'm no king, and I have no woman.
-对我毫无意义 -乌特雷德大人
-It means nothing. - Lord Uhtred.
我已吩咐儿子训练王子
I told my son to train yours.
瓦莎可以服侍你
While you are here, take Wassa as your serving woman.
-当自己家 -关于艾索斯坦，我想说一件事
-Make this fortress your home. -I wish to say one thing of Aethelstan.
他已经不像从前那般无忧无虑
He is not quite the carefree boy you raised.
他现在非常虔诚
He has grown very much into his faith.
奥斯华兄弟会对他影响极深
The Brotherhood of Oswald exert great influence.
我吓跑不少这种人，修士都莫名怕我
I have scared off such men before. For some reason, monks find me terrifying.
让我们再次拥立新王吧
- Let's go play kingmaker. - Once again.
（格拉斯顿伯里）
（威塞克斯王国，格拉斯顿伯里）
父王去世了？不可能
My father? No, that cannot be.
上帝说他会活过冬天的
I thought God had given him the winter.
艾索斯坦大人 你得赶快到威塞克斯加冕
Lord Aethelstan, you should make haste to Wessex for coronation.
你弟弟正在召集人手
Your brother gathers men.
务必趁他结成大军前 返回温彻斯特登基为王
Establish yourself at Winchester before he raises an army.
我们会遵从上帝的命令 皮尔里各神父
We will leave when God commands us to leave, Father Pyrlig.
上帝尚未要求我们离去
And that command has not been given.
祷告完就回去吧
Return when you have prayed.
我该离开吗？
Do I depart?
只有圣经知道
Only the book has answers.
来吧
Play.
你被指引至《马太福音》第57节
You have been guided to the Book of Matthew, verse 157.
“于是耶稣动身前往推罗与西顿海岸”
"Then Jesus went thence and departed into the coasts of Tyre and Sidon."
上帝要你战斗
God wants you to fight.
（艾尔斯伯里）
（麦西亚王国，艾尔斯伯里）
真是谢了
Oh. Thank you, lady.
停，有何贵干？
Halt. State your business here.
我们听说有人在招募战士
We heard a man is looking for fighters.
想来赚点钱
We come to make some coin.
进去吧
Go on.
-这里简直成了地狱 -爱德华任它凋零
-This place has fallen to shit. - Edward left it to decline.
幸好艾塞弗蕾德不必见证这一切
I'm glad Aethelflaed is not here to see it.
大家都接到消息了
Word has spread.
我敢说一半的人都是熟面孔
I swear I've fought half these men.
-这不是普通的招兵买马 -是要开战了
This is not someone trying to recruit. This is preparing for a battle.
那个年轻人就是艾弗维尔
That is the youth Aelfweard.
去探听他的计划
Go see what men know of his plans.
我给你看一把剑!
I'll show you a sword!
-你剑上那个是琥珀？ -怎么卖？
-Is that amber in your sword? -How much do you want for it?
-回去喝奶吧  -艾格，冷静
- Go home to your mothers. - Edgar! No.
威佛！
Wilfrid!
你叫我？
Do you speak to me, friend?
抱歉，我以为你是威佛
Your pardon. I thought you were Wilfrid.
我们曾在泰腾豪之战并肩作战
A great man I fought with at Tettenhall.
你打过泰腾豪之战？
Wait, you were at Tettenhall?
我父亲也有参战
My father was there.
-你现在为谁效命？ -艾弗…什么的
-Who do you fight for now? -Aelf… something?
-萨克逊人名字都很像 -要出征威塞克斯的艾弗维尔？
-Saxon names are much alike. -The Aelf who marches on Wessex?
看来你们没听说
You haven't heard.
他不打算攻打威塞克斯
No one's marching on Wessex.
现在的计划是把艾索斯坦引过来
I'm told the new plan is to lure Aethelstan here.
艾索斯坦要来了
Aethelstan is on his way.
他接下艾弗维尔发的战帖
Aelfweard challenged him to battle, and he's accepted.
他为什么要迎战？
Why would he agree to that?
他还年轻，中了圈套
Because he's young, and they've baited him.
他们派人埋伏在山丘 打算在城门逮他
They plan to snare him between the gate and men hidden in the hills.
我们要在他抵达前拿下控制权
Then we take control before he arrives.
大人，光靠我们拿不下这座城镇
We can't seize this town with just us, Lord.
没有那个必要
We do not need to seize the town.
兄弟，要不要小赌一下？
Hey! Can I tempt you to play for money, friend?
把他们绑起来、门锁好 艾索斯坦抵达前不要轻举妄动
Tie them up and secure the bolt. Stay low until Aethelstan arrives.
如果有床就归我
If there's a bed, it's mine.
他来了
He's here.
发出警报！大军接近南门！
Raise the alarm! Soldiers approach the southern gate!
站住，艾尔斯伯里现在效忠于我
Come no further! Aegelesburg is loyal to me now.
我们不跟私生子谈判
We do not negotiate with bastards.
也拒绝投降
Nor do we surrender.
-你只能饿死我们 -弟弟，我不是傻子
-You'll have to starve us out. -I am not foolish, brother.
我早预料你会设下陷阱
I assumed you would place a trap.
把我牵制在此，再从后方包夹
Perhaps delay me here until your forces could attack at rearguard.
把埋伏的人带上来
Show him what's left of his men!
立刻投降
You can yield now,
否则我们破门而入，血洗这里
or we destroy the gate and kill all your men.
城门牢不可破 我绝不投降
The gates will hold. No yield will come.
那你就跟城门一起下地狱吧
Then you will be destroyed.
准备开门
Get ready to open the door.
我才是合法的王位继承人 你母亲是婊子
I am the rightful king. Your mother was a whore.
有良知的人都明白，而且你没有盟友
All good men know it. You have no allies.
艾弗维尔大人
Lord Aelfweard.
-我是贝班堡的乌特雷德 -乌特雷德
-I'm Uhtred of Bebbanburg. -Uhtred.
你知道我向来直言不讳
You know me as a man who speaks the truth,
相信我，为了所有人好，放弃吧
so hear me when I say, for the common good, stand down.
我的人控制了城门，你是以寡敌众
My men control the gate. You're outnumbered on all sides.
投降吧
Yield.
让这一切和平落幕
Let this end with peace.
投降吧，弟弟
Give yourself to me, brother.
我不会追究的
Then it is over.
请原谅我的无能
Forgive me for my failings,
请安慰我母亲的族人
and give comfort to my mother's kin.
告诉他们我已被流放
Tell them of my exile
以及我们曾为了光宗耀祖而奋斗
and how we sought to honor our discarded bloodline.
-为威塞克斯而战！
-For Wessex! - For Wessex!
乌特雷德大人
Lord Uhtred,
打开城门
open the gate.
-不！ -我是上帝选择的合法继承人
-No! - God chose me rightful heir.
艾索斯坦！
Aethelstan!
上
Advance!
杀个片甲不留
Leave no enemy alive!
大人，快阻止这场闹剧
Lord, stop this madness!
住手！
Stop!
艾索斯坦！
Aethelstan!
退后，躲起来
Get back! Hide!
我投降，拜托不要…
- I submit! Please don't--
艾索斯坦
Aethelstan!
求求你，饶了我吧
Please, show mercy!
不！
No!
住手！他们已经投降了！
Stop! They're surrendering!
艾索斯坦！
Aethelstan!
-Aethelsta--
大人，救救我们
Lord! Lord, help us!
艾索斯坦！
Aethelstan!
艾索斯坦
-叫你的人住手 -乌特雷德，你来做什么？
-Stand down your men. - Uhtred, why are you here?
我来阻止战争，敌人已经投降了
To stop this. Your enemy has surrendered.
叫你的人住手
Halt your men.
-让他过来，去叫停 -是，大人
-Let him approach and call a halt. - Yes, my lord.
-你怎么了？ -你才怎么了？
-What happened to you?
-没必要杀了你弟 -当然有必要
-You had no need to kill your brother. -I did, or in time, he would return.
-他迟早会卷土重来 -你没有遵守诺言
-You dishonored your word. -I did not.
我叫他投降，没说要留他活口
I told him to yield. I did not say he would survive.
我们本来就不打算让他活命 大人，请撤回命令
It was never our plan to let him live. Lord, reverse the order.
我们即将击溃敌人
We are close to routing them.
-那些佣兵跟你无冤无仇 -你不找他帮忙是对的
-Hired men have no quarrel with you. -You were right not to seek his help.
杀了一百个父亲 就会有三百个儿子反抗你
You kill 100 fathers, you give 300 sons a reason to defy you.
动动脑啊！
Think!
现在正是统一的时候
Now's the time to unify.
乌特雷德说得有道理
Uhtred may be right in this matter.
我是以过来人的身分提出劝告
I speak only as a man who has made mistakes before.
-我是贝班堡的… -我知道你是谁
-I'm Uhtred of-- -I know who you are.
乌特雷德，这位是英格曼德大人
Uhtred, this is Lord Ingilmundr.
他是了不起的指挥官 也是我的好朋友
A great commander and a great friend to me.
那他也是我的朋友了
Then a friend to me.
你怎么会有丹麦人的名字？
Why the Danish name?
我是萨克逊人养大的丹麦人
Born to a Dane, but raised a Saxon.
艾佛雷德的写作使我皈依基督教
I found Christ through the works of Alfred,
你在罗马的儿子也透过文字启发了我
and indeed through the writings of your son in Rome.
你一定以他为傲
You must be proud of him.
他是货真价实的学者
He is a true scholar.
我只是赋予他生命的粗人
I'm just the fool who made him.
英格曼德掌管了 威勒尔半岛塞沃尔的驻军
Ingilmundr holds the garrison at Thelwael on the Wirral.
他认识许多我们在朗可法的旧识
He knows many of the people we knew from Rumcofa.
他们都是好人，希望还能见面
Good people. I should like to see them again.
好，先向新王宣誓诺桑比亚的忠诚吧
Yes. Perhaps after you've sworn Northumbria to the new king.
遵守你的诺言
Honor your word.
把你欠他父亲的还回来
Swear to Aethelstan what you denied his father.
交出你的土地 让英格兰成为完整的国家
Cede your lands and make England whole.
就像你说的
As you say,
是时候统一了
it is the time for unity.
我会向国王效忠，但你尚未登基
I will swear to a king, and you are not yet crowned.
我拒绝以这副血淋淋的模样立誓
Nor will I kneel to you covered in blood.
我会在温彻斯特的大厅宣布放弃领地
I will renounce my lands in the Great Hall at Winchester.
-我们不需要繁文缛节 -乌特雷德是信守承诺的人
-It doesn't need to be done with ceremony. -But Uhtred is a man of his word.
来温彻斯特找我
Come to Winchester.
把伤口治好
Heal the wound.
他怎么知道我们要来？
How did he know we were coming here?
他总是有办法保护我
He's always found a way to protect me.
也许他派人盯着你
Perhaps he has friends who keep one eye on you.
我母亲也这样
My mother was the same.
真窝心，你还听他的话
It's touching, how you still defer to him.
-他一直都忠心耿耿 -你太高尚了，竟然相信他
-He's been steadfast a long time. -And noble that you trust him.
他可是背叛了你父亲
Given all that went on with your father.
（史特灵）
（苏格兰王国，史特灵）
哪个王子赢了？
Which boy prevailed?
艾索斯坦
Aethelstan.
他冷血地杀了自己的手足 即将登基为萨克逊王
Killed his brother in cold blood and will now claim the Saxon crown.
看来大势已定 有和平条约的消息吗？
Then it's settled. Any word on renewal of the treaty?
去催促温彻斯特
Push Winchester.
-动用你的关系 -陛下，还有一件事
-Make contact. -Lord, we've had word of something else.
-丹麦人安拉夫想要谈谈 -那个食人族？
-The Dane, Anlaf, seeks a meeting. -The one who eats the flesh of men?
他还找了曼岛、昔得兰 和奥克尼的国王
An assembly with you, and the kings of Man, Shetland, and Orkney.
我一个基督徒 才不会傻呼呼去见一群丹麦国王
I will not be the lone Christian lured to meet Dane kings.
他们也许有不错的提议
They might offer something of interest.
去跟萨克逊人谈和平条约
Seek to renew a peace with Saxons.
爱德华维持了停战协议 他儿子没理由打破
Edward kept the truce. We have no reason to think his son will not.
我会去传话
I'll send word.
他亲手杀了自己的兄弟
His own flesh, put to the knife.
-他比你说的还要残忍 -他变冷酷了
-He is more brutal than you suggested. -His heart has hardened.
反对他的人会更不满
Which should harden those against him.
-不列颠诸王都接到消息了吗？ -他们当耳边风
-Do other kings in Britain hear our call? -They pretend to be deaf to us.
-其实都听进去了 -是该如此
-But I know they listen. -They should.
艾索斯坦将变得贪婪
Aethelstan will become greedy.
你对野心再了解不过，父亲
You would know ambition, Father.
等你继承了我的土地，你也会明白的
Eh, and when my lands are yours, you will know it too.
回去温彻斯特
Return to Winchester.
盯紧每一个人
Watch everyone.
有消息随时回报
And bring me word when there's word to tell.
-父亲，你受伤了？ -小伤
- Father, have you been injured?
拜托告诉我这不是真的
-Nothing that will not heal. - Tell me the news is wrong.
艾索斯坦杀了他的手足？
-Did Aethelstan turn on his own blood? - Yes.
对，艾弗维尔死了 艾德蒙千万不能回到温彻斯特
-Aelfweard did not survive. -Then Edmund cannot return to Winchester.
他将永远被视为威胁
He will always be seen as a rival.
艾索斯坦向来疼爱你儿子
Aethelstan has always shown great affection for your son.
她说得对
But she is right.
他受人影响了
He has fallen under an influence.
我会在贝班堡待到情势安全为止
I shall not leave Bebbanburg until the threat passes.
-这里永远欢迎你 -情势会好转的
-You're welcome here as long as you wish. - And it will pass.
国王的职责将导正艾索斯坦
The duties of kingship will focus Aethelstan's mind.
我该回南方了
But I should return south.
我会确认他的状态
I will assess the mood.
♪ Hallelujah ♪
全能永生的上帝
Almighty and everlasting God,
请以恩典与祝福洗净祢的仆人
pour out the spirit of thy grace and blessing upon this, thy servant,
艾索斯坦国王
King Aethelstan.
我们于今日举行按手礼，加冕他为王
That, as by the imposition of our hands, he is this day crowned king.
蒙上帝圣宠
So he may, by thy sanctification,
他将透过基督，我们的主 继续做祢拣选的仆人，直到永远
continue always thy chosen servant, through Christ, our Lord.
请赐予他亚伯拉罕的信念
Grant him the faith of Abraham,
所罗门的智慧
the wisdom of Solomon,
以及大卫的勇气
the courage of David.
Vivat Rex!
（二：威塞克斯、麦西亚 与东英格兰国王）
你没来观礼
You were not there.
这是我们盼望已久的一刻
This moment was all we had talked of.
-你却缺席了 -对
-And you were not there. -No.
我在这里
I was here.
圣经的召唤至高无上
The call of the scripture always comes first.
你也同意吧？
You believe that, don't you?
当然了
Yes, yes, of course.
那你将成为伟大的英格兰国王
Then you will be a great king of England.
你会像艾佛雷德一样受人赞颂
And all will speak of you as they did Alfred.
乌特雷德履行承诺了吗？
Does Uhtred stand by his word?
不，乌特雷德没来
No. Uhtred has not come.
-他显然认为… -他想继续在自己的领土称王
-Clearly, he-- -He wishes to remain king in his own land.
愿上帝保佑他不受虚荣蒙蔽
May God protect him from his vanity.
对你而言，这是残酷的事实
But towards you, it is a cruelty.
我感到非常遗憾，来
And I am sorry. Here. Come. Come.
他竟然折磨你善良的灵魂
What torture to enact on so kind a soul.
-我以为你们都遗弃我了 -我绝不会那么做
-I thought you had both abandoned me. -Of course I would not.
但我很讶异乌特雷德竟如此愚蠢
I'm just surprised Uhtred could be so foolish.
我以为岁月能使他增长智慧
You would've thought his years would make him wiser.
也许在他眼中，你依旧是个孩子
Perhaps he still sees the boy you once were,
而不是顶天立地的男子汉
and not the man you have become.
大人
Lord.
虽然比不上蛇息剑…
It's not Serpent's Breath, but…
但这把更轻盈、更锋利 镶有石榴石
it's lighter, it's sharper, and it's got a garnet.
取个名字吧
Give it a name.
斩魂剑
Manslayer.
绝后剑
Ball-taker.
乌特雷德，乌特雷德之剑
Uhtred, Sword of Uhtred.
你笑了，大人
You actually smiled, Lord.
也许失去蛇息剑是个预兆 代表我该退出战场了
Perhaps losing my sword was a sign that my battle days are over.
这时候挑衅国王可不妙
A bad time to provoke the king.
我没有挑衅他
I did not provoke him.
我是给他时间证明自己不是暴君
I'm simply giving him time to prove he's not a tyrant.
-否则… -怎么样？
-Otherwise… -Otherwise what?
“七王丧钟”，原因是什么？
"Seven kings must die." For what?
-你妻子看到了什么？ -什么都没有
-What did your wife see? -She sees nothing.
我发誓
I swear.
他们在庆祝什么？
What do they celebrate?
驯马成功
The breaking of the horses.
感谢奥斯柏如此照顾艾德蒙
Thank Osbert for the care he has shown Edmund.
他是贝班堡的一分子了
He's part of Bebbanburg now.
你们都是
You both are.
对，我儿子变了许多
Yes, my son is quite changed.
他在宫里的忧郁一扫而空
There was a somberness at the palace that has lifted.
因为这里空气清新
It's the air here.
使人神清气爽
Brings out good spirits in everyone.
Hyah!
你似乎更开朗了
You yourself seem happier.
没错，乌特雷德大人
I am, Lord Uhtred.
我已经放下悲痛，而且…
Some grief has passed, and I feel…
更有信心面对世界了
more ready for the world.
控制马匹，很好
Control! Good!
主啊，请怜悯我们的灵魂 宽恕我们的罪恶
Forgive us these sins that we commit.
我们能得到宽恕吗？
Will we be forgiven?
我们罪孽深重
Our sin weighs heavy.
对
Yes, it does.
但别忘了
But remember,
上帝会进行审判
God holds us in the balance.
信仰能抵销一切罪过
Every sin can be weighed against an act of faith.
增加信仰，就能减少罪过
Grow the faith and the sin is diminished.
如果罪孽深重到无法饶恕呢？
What if the shadow of sin obscures the faith?
跟我来
Come.
也许你该实现祖父对英格兰的梦想
Perhaps return to your grandfather's vision for England.
也许让异教徒皈依基督教 才是当务之急
Perhaps now there is an urgency to bring the pagans to light.
那样会…
Will that
洗净我吗？
cleanse me?
你和我？
Us?
当然，福音传得越远，信仰就越强
Well, surely the greater the lands, the greater the faith.
把艾佛雷德的梦想发扬光大
Go beyond what Alfred dreamed of.
放眼上帝创造的土地 而非人类划分的领土
Look to the islands God made, not the countries ordained by men,
引领所有人成为祂的子民
and bring all to Christianity.
当你接受审判时
So when you are judged,
就能得到赦免
you will be found in balance.
大方拥抱罪过…
And thus may accept both the sin…
勇敢出征吧
and the conquest against it.
（诺桑比亚南方边境）
大人
Lord!
别说了
Stop.
你们在聊什么？
What do you talk of?
天啊，夫人，请恕我无礼
Oh my faith, Lady. I cannot lie.
这里的妇女都很关心乌特雷德大人 希望他能找个女伴
The ladies here care for Lord Uhtred and wish keenly he would find a woman.
那她们要失望了
Well, they shall be sore of heart.
先王遗孀不会嫁给领主的
The widow of a king will not marry a lord.
我应该多加注意言行举止
I shall have to be more careful in how I conduct myself.
夫人，八卦还不是最可怕的
It is not the gossips you should fear, Lady.
和平的日子可能不会长久
This peace may not sustain.
乌特雷德大人怠慢了国王
Lord Uhtred has snubbed the king.
乌特雷德心爱的女性 都会成为敌人的目标
The women Uhtred has affection for become a target for his enemies.
希崔里克
- Sihtric! -Sh-sh.
有什么消息？
What have you learnt?
艾索斯坦占领了埃弗维治
Aethelstan has claimed Eoferwic.
他说朗弗德死了，没有国王 所以领土归他
He says since Rognvaldr is dead, there is no king, so it belongs to him.
埃弗维治？
Eoferwic?
他们现在认我为领主 艾索斯坦知道的
They see me as their lord now. Aethelstan knows this.
他要求所有人进贡
He is demanding all come with tribute.
不只是萨克逊首领，是全不列颠国王
Not just Saxon chiefs, but all kings of Britain.
包括整片大陆和所有海岛
All the mainland and all the outlying islands.
大人
Lord?
在这里称王吧
Declare yourself king here.
像你祖先那样
Like your forebears.
不，他可是艾索斯坦
No. This is Aethelstan.
如果他误入歧途，我就必须点醒他
If he chooses the wrong path, I must tell him.
大人
Lord.
（埃弗维治）
（诺桑比亚王国，约克）
“根据新法令，全境皆须纳税”
"There went out a decree that all the world should be taxed."
不必进贡，通通回村子去
You owe no tribute! Return to your villages.
-乌特雷德，冷静点 -皮尔里各，进贡是怎么回事？
-Uhtred! Calm yourself. -Pyrlig? What is this tribute?
他说是为了建教堂 小声点，到处都是间谍
He says it is to build churches, but, please, there are spies everywhere.
告诉你家的兔崽子他太小看苏格兰了
Tell your arseling apprentice he's badly misjudged the mood of Scotland.
这么生气
You seem upset.
我们来谈和平条约
We came to renew our treaty.
却被晾了好几天，还被说是来乞讨的
Instead, we've been left waiting for days, only to be told we are supplicants.
劝你们小心点
I would be careful.
有人来找我们结盟
We've had other offers of alliance.
艾索斯坦为何这么做？ 他说是为了团结基督徒
-Why is Aethelstan doing this? -He says to unite Christians.
他在祷告中不断提到赎罪
And in his prayers, he talks much of atonement.
赎罪？什么罪？
Atonement? For what?
他弟弟的死？他的私生子身分？
The death of his brother, the bastardy of his parentage?
我不清楚
I do not know.
我和艾德汉大人天天在劝他
Lord Aldhelm and I try daily to dissuade,
但他满口征服天下、强迫洗礼
but there is talk of conquest and forced baptism.
-他在哪里？ -恶魔石
-Where is he? -The Devil's Stones.
他认为自己能战胜恶魔
He thinks he fights the devil.
这简直胡来，艾德汉
This is madness. Aldhelm.
这些石头已经耸立好几个世代了
These stones have stood for generations.
显然对上帝不敬
They are an insult to God, apparently.
那是斯特拉斯克莱德国王欧文吗？
Is that Owain, King of Strathclyde?
艾索斯坦要他亲眼见证
Aethelstan wanted him to witness it.
这些是他祖先的杰作
They were built by his forebears.
他想要羞辱权贵？
He is seeking to humiliate powerful men?
海威尔国王
King Hywel.
（四：威尔斯国王）
他竟然要威尔斯称臣？
He dares ask submission from Wealas?
你们对麦西亚有功
After all you did for Mercia?
乌特雷德，我能怎么办？
What choice do I have, Uhtred?
他把我儿子抓去温彻斯特
He took my son to Winchester.
他把你儿子当人质？
He is keeping your son hostage?
抓走儿子，等于抓走未来的国王
You take the son, you take a future king.
-我只能听从他的命令 -我会告诉他这种事不可原谅
-Now I am forced to follow his bidding. -I will tell him this cannot stand.
海威尔国王 我保证威尔斯的忠诚不会被践踏
King Hywel, I swear, Wealas's faithfulness will not be spat on.
我们的诗人曾说过
Our poets spoke this.
萨克逊人将为了打造自己的国家 而摧毁我们
That a Saxon would break us all to build their country.
这不只是萨克逊人的国家
This is not just a Saxon country.
艾德汉，带我去见他 我要阻止这一切
Aldhelm, get me close to him. I will stop this.
站住，退后
Halt. Stay back.
让开，国王要召见乌特雷德
Step aside! The king requested Uhtred speak with him.
艾索斯坦国王
King Aethelstan!
陛下
Lord King,
我想跟你私下谈谈
let me speak with you alone.
-你不该侵占我的领土 -你也不该违背誓言
You should not have stepped on my land.
你当年羞辱父王
You should not have broken your word, humiliated me,
现在又羞辱我
as you humiliated my father.
我是要点醒你，你误入歧途了
I'm trying to make you see you're on the wrong path.
-你对英格曼德唯命是从 -我只听从上帝
-You do the bidding of Ingilmundr-- -I do the bidding of the Lord.
你打算强迫丹麦人改变信仰？
Do you really seek to convert Danes?
-我没教你尊重两个字吗？ -很多丹麦人欢迎上帝
-Did I teach you nothing of respect? -Many Danes welcome the Lord.
-宫里的人都很感激 -也有人不想改变信仰，你心知肚明
-Those in my court thank me for it. -Many do not wish it, and you know this.
艾索斯坦，你明明知道的
Aethelstan, you've always known it.
-连艾佛雷德都尊重这一点 -我要赎的罪更多
-Even Alfred respected this. -I have more to atone for than Alfred.
谁说的？英格曼德？
Who tells you this? Ingilmundr?
他是不是说你不能没有他的指引？
Does he tell you you are damned without his guidance?
我看过太多人被神棍耍得团团转了
For I've seen before men under the spell of those who claim to know the gods.
他是我忠实的朋友
He has been a great friend to me.
艾索斯坦，你爱睡谁都行
Aethelstan, hump who you wish,
但千万别被觊觎权力的人…
but do not fall under the influence of those who seek power--
是谁放出这种恶毒的指控？
Who makes such vicious claim against me?
-没人 -是谁在撒谎？
-No one. -Who tells such lies?
-没有任何传闻 -艾德汉大人是间谍吗？
-It has not been talked of. -Lord Aldhelm, does he spy for…
是谁传了什么？传多久了？
What has been said, by who, and for how long?
没有任何传闻 我也不在乎，我只在乎你
No one has said anything. I care not for that, but for you.
艾索斯坦，你很善良，但心肠太软
Aethelstan, you are a kind man, but you are tenderhearted,
英格曼德在为自己和兄弟会谋权
and Ingilmundr is seeking power for himself and for his brotherhood.
这是说谎、诽谤
Lies. Lies and ignominy.
我没有诽谤，他让你背弃家人
There's no ignominy. He just turns you from your kin.
你才背弃了你的国王！
And you are turned from your king!
你打算自己称王
You seek to be one yourself.
陛下，现在要为土地祝圣
Lord, they consecrate the ground
请你赐予祝福
and would request you to give the blessing.
没问题
Yes, of course.
让诺桑比亚国王反省一下自己的错误
Let us leave the King of Northumbria to think on his errors.
我对王位没兴趣
I have no dream to be a king.
我只想保护你
Only to protect you.
你上次去艾尔斯伯里保护他 不是被年轻人毒打一顿？
Like you ran to protect him in Aegelesburg and ended up being beaten by boys?
剑都被小鬼头抢走了 还有资格说话吗？
Should he really take counsel from a man who loses his sword to a child?
诺桑比亚需要骁勇善战的领主
Northumbria needs a lord with lust for battle.
据说安拉夫已上岸 他将大肆烧杀掳掠
There are rumors Anlaf has arrived and will come Viking.
别以为你们有同样的信仰 他就会饶你一命
Do not think he will spare you just because you follow the same gods.
留他一晚，逼他在日出宣誓效忠
Keep him here a night and make him swear at dawn.
你迟早会来乞求他的帮忙
In time, you will come begging for his help.
父亲都会倒下
As all fathers fall,
由儿子取而代之
and all sons take their place.
英格曼德大人宣布你是上帝的敌人
Lord Ingilmundr has declared you an enemy of God
还煽动追随者杀了你
to incite his followers to kill you.
艾索斯坦不会允许这种事
Aethelstan would not allow it.
所以英格曼德才要装作没有涉入其中
Which is why Ingilmundr seeks to keep his hands clean of it
他已经离开了
and has left the camp.
去哪里？
To go where?
这边
This way.
上去吧，没有守卫
Go up and around. There's no guard.
就是他
Him. That is the man.
你跟异教徒说了什么？
What did you speak of with the pagan?
有骑兵接近
Horsemen approach!
停，报上名来
Stay back from my gates and tell me who you are.
我是英格曼德大人 应乌特雷德大人的要求前来
Lord Ingilmundr, and I come at Lord Uhtred's request.
他要重新向国王宣誓效忠 在埃弗维治耽搁了
He's delayed in Eoferwic as he renews his vow to the king.
所以请我来保护你
He asked I help protect you.
保护我？
Protect from what?
据说狼战士在德文特河畔上岸了
There is a rumor of Wolf-Warriors landed near Derwent.
打开城门
Open the gate! Open the gate!
不要这么做
Do not give the order.
我们曾经同甘共苦
Think on all we have shared.
你迷失自我了，艾索斯坦
You're lost from yourself, Aethelstan.
我们一起对抗…
We fought together--
你放话中伤我，还跟乌特雷德密谋
And despite this, you drip poison against me and plot with Uhtred.
-不是的 -是
-No. -Yes.
-不是 -是
-No. -Yes!
你背叛了我，艾德汉
You turned your back, Aldhelm.
我只好回敬你
Now I turn mine.
英格曼德大人
Lord Ingilmundr,
真是好消息 乌特雷德大人要称臣了
you bring welcome news of Lord Uhtred's supplication.
你愿意伴我南下，让我亲眼见证吗？
Will you journey south with me to let me bear witness to it?
夫人，大伙都骑累了 至少让我们休息一天吧
Lady, we have ridden hard to get here. At least let us rest a day or so.
可是我被困在贝班堡好久了
Oh, but I have been trapped in Bebbanburg a good while.
相信我，此地不宜久留
Believe me, you do not want to find yourself here longer than intended.
-他们接到警告了！ -上！
-They've been warned! - Now!
我们抢先赶到了
We overtook you on the road.
你对艾索斯坦的控制就到此为止了
Whatever power you hold over Aethelstan,
today it ends.
我的剑
My sword!
你还想上英灵殿
You still believe in Valhalla!
艾索斯坦很在乎你，我可不要他怨我
Aethelstan cares for you. I will not divide us further.
把他关在下面
Put him below.
基督徒，快来救我！ 你们的主人是谁？
Christians amongst you, defend me! Who is your Lord?
乌特雷德大人还是耶稣基督？
Lord Uhtred or the Lord Jesus Christ?
贝班堡人民不会为了信仰而分裂
The people of Bebbanburg will not be divided by faith.
蠢蛋，起来抗争！
Rise up, you fools!
去通知国王释放条件
Tell the king the terms of his release.
他要和诺桑比亚达成和平协定 确立边境
He makes peace with Northumbria and guarantees the border.
-不得强迫任何人改变信仰 -是的，大人
-No one is forced to follow his god. -Yes, Lord.
条件真多
Quite a price.
-艾索斯坦会同意吗？ -希望如此
-Will Aethelstan agree? - Let us hope so.
他现在抛弃朋友速度挺快的
He seems to discard his friends rather quickly now.
你祝福了卑微的灵魂
Truly, you bless an unworthy soul.
-愿上帝赏赐你的仁慈 -阿门
-May God reward your kindness. -Amen.
（曼岛）
（诸王集会）
（五：奥克尼国王）
（六：昔得兰国王）
艾索斯坦背弃了朋友
Aethelstan turns against his friends.
妄想成为全天下的帝王
Succumbs to a wild dream to be a monarch for all your land.
他迟早会去找你，昔得兰国王
In time, he will come for you, Shetland.
还有你，奥克尼国王
You, Orkney.
他会夺走你祖先的领土 称之为不列颠
He will take what belonged to your forebears and call it Britain.
不可能
No.
那个萨克逊乡巴佬鲜少出航
He barely sets his foot upon the water. Saxon country folk.
我们可以赶跑他们
We can repel them.
我的提议不只如此
我提议征服回去
I'm not talking of repelling, but of meeting conquest with conquest.
苏格兰不加入
Scotland rejects your offer.
我们不跟异教徒 联手攻打毫无威胁的人
We cannot join with pagans to attack a man who's not threatened us.
基督徒不会选择战争
Christians do not choose war.
战争即将爆发
War is coming.
你只能选边站
You only have to choose a side.
愿上帝与你同在
God be with you.
石头滚开了，就像圣经那样
The stone was rolled away, as in the scripture.
一定是天使显灵
It can only be the work of an angel.
这边，大人，快来看看宝物
This way, Lord. Come and see the treasures.
大人
Lord!
他怎么说？
What word from Eoferwic?
他接受条件吗？
Does he accept my terms?
我没有消息回报
I have no news.
艾索斯坦回温彻斯特了
Aethelstan is said to have returned to Winchester.
姑且当成好兆头吧
Well, let us take it as a good sign.
少了他的影响 艾索斯坦应该能清醒点
Perhaps without his shadow, Aethelstan sees more clearly.
你们来这里做什么？
What trouble brings you out here?
村民找到异教徒的银子
The villagers were hunting for pagan silver.
他们宣称是奇蹟
Now they're saying it's a miracle.
让诺桑比亚国王通过
Make way for the King of Northumbria.
我就说吧
I told you.
他们都把你当国王
They think of you as a king.
他们会不会想分一半？
Do you think they hope to keep half for themselves?
说不定是他们从贝班堡拿来的
They likely took it from Bebbanburg in the first place.
我要以艾索斯坦国王的名义拘捕你
You are detained in the name of King Aethelstan.
大人
Lord.
这是圈套
We've been lured here.
你也觉得？
You think?
大人，对不起
Lord, I'm sorry!
抱歉，大人
I'm sorry, Lord.
俘虏说我必须这么做 否则会受地狱之火吞噬
The prisoner told me I had to, or I'd burn in the fires of hell.
我死都不会下令打开城门
I will never order to open the gates.
确定？
Really?
这是国王送的礼物
A gift from the king.
艾索斯坦杀了他？
Aethelstan did this?
这就是叛徒的下场
It's what he does to traitors.
打开城门，否则我杀了你父亲
Open the gates or I slaughter your father.
乖乖配合我就饶他一命
Comply and he will be spared.
不要开
Do not open.
-我会当你的面杀了他 -不要开！
-I can kill him in front of you. -Do not open!
-你决定吧 -奥斯柏，不要开门！
-The choice is yours. - Osbert! Do not open!
父亲，既然你不在，这里由我做主
In your absence, Father, I command here.
-我下令开城门 -不要啊！
And I command that we open.
不！
-No! - No, no, no!
放下武器
Drop your sword.
前进
Move.
不可以
No.
艾索斯坦呢？
Where is Aethelstan?
别急
In time.
把艾格芙夫人带过来
Bring me the Lady Eadgifu.
过来
Come.
我自己会走
I can walk.
动手吧
Go on.
杀了我
Kill me.
我要把你送到圣岛的修道院
You are to be placed in the community on Lindisfarne
保护你的贞洁
to protect your virtue.
你跟异教徒睡了吗，夫人？
Did you hump the heathen, Lady?
承认吧
Confess.
我承认
I confess
我向上帝祈祷你早日惨死
to have prayed for your excruciating death.
没有吗？太可惜了
A no, then. You should have tried when you had the chance.
你儿子将加入我在塞沃尔的驻军
We're taking your son to my garrison
-接受战斗训练
at Thelwael where he will be trained for battle.
-不，请饶了他
No. No. Please.
-动起来 -还有你儿子
- Move! -Your son also.
不，艾德蒙是艾佛雷德的血脉
No. Edmund is the blood of Alfred.
他不是盾墙的料
He should not be fodder for a shield wall! Please!
-我求你了 -我会照顾他
- I will take care of him. -Please!
乌特雷德之子将为威塞克斯而战
The son of Uhtred stands for Wessex.
冷静
Hey! Hey!
我们对你另有打算
You, we have a plan for.
-他打算淹死我吗？ -我从来都摸不透他
- Am I to be drowned in the sea? - I never quite know his mind.
别惩罚贝班堡的人 这是我跟他的战争
Do not punish those in Bebbanburg.
他的战场在别处
-His fight is with me. -His fight is elsewhere.
真走运，苏格兰就这么近
How lucky we have found ourselves so close to the Scottish border.
别入侵苏格兰，你会失去上百名士兵
No, do not invade Scotland. You will lose hundreds of men.
还会引发数个世代的战争
And unleash a war for generations.
国王没有后顾之忧，这也使他更强大
The king has no successor to fear for. It makes him strong.
想办法保护我们的儿子 别反抗，听他的话
Do whatever you must to protect our sons. Do not fight him. Just capitulate.
不要做傻事
Anything else is foolish.
-艾德汉没有背叛你 -你们全背叛了我
-Aldhelm never betrayed you. -All of you betrayed me.
亏我当你们是朋友
All those I thought as friends.
在贝班堡前对我称臣，我就饶你一命
Swear now, before Bebbanburg, and I will spare your life.
-我拒绝 -那我只能杀了你
-No. -Then you leave me with no choice.
艾索斯坦
Aethelstan.
我办不到
I cannot.
-我来效劳… -免了
-Let me offer my-- -No.
把他剥光
Take everything from him.
你被放逐了，别再踏上我的土地
I banish you from my lands to travel the earth and seas alone.
否则你儿子将小命不保
On pain of murder of your son.
谁敢给他温饱，就是与我为敌
Let none feed or clothe him, lest become my enemy.
走吧
Go.
趁我还没改变心意
Before this mercy vanishes.
回头吧，现在还来得及
Turn back. There is still time.
苏格兰人不是威胁
The Scots are no threat.
这是造孽啊，陛下
This will damn you, Lord King.
驱逐异教徒也许是正义之举
To save us from the pagans can be a just endeavor.
但背叛基督徒是不敬之举
But to turn on other Christians is ungodly.
你的手下并不想打这场仗
Your men do not want this fight.
也许我需要更好的战士
Well, perhaps I need better men.
也许我该把你儿子找来
Perhaps I should summon your son.
陛下
Lord King!
艾索斯坦攻打了苏格兰低地的聚落
Aethelstan has attacked settlements in the lowlands.
我们必须反击
He cannot raid us without reply.
要不要通知安拉夫 你准备出席诸王集会了？
Do I tell Anlaf you are ready to meet with him and the other kings?
丹麦屠夫乌特雷德
Uhtred the Daneslayer.
你在本夫利特之役杀了
You killed my cousin Gelf at the battle of Beamfleot.
我堂弟葛夫
…the battle of Beamfleot.
去回报找到他了
Send word we have found him.
我超讨厌葛夫
I hated Gelf.
葛夫，葛夫…
Gelf, Gelf…
带他去见国王
Take him to the king.
你们要带我去哪？
Where are you taking me?
最北端的岛屿
To the very north of these islands.
（昔得兰）
（昔得兰群岛）
你们在庆祝什么？
What do you give thanks for?
庆祝大战即将开打
For the great battle to come.
通知首领诺桑比亚国王来了
Tell the jarl we're here with the King of Northumbria.
-这里全是昔得兰人？ -也有曼岛人和奥克尼人
- All folk of Shetland? - Some of Man and Orkney join us.
他们的国王也在
With their kings.
这就是…
Is this who they claim?
诺桑比亚国王？
The King of Northumbria?
对，没错
Aye, it's him.
-我并非国王 -对
-I am no king. - No.
但你有机会称王
But you could be.
坐吧，我们是你的朋友
Sit. You are amongst friends.
你竟然加入异教徒？
You join with pagans?
艾索斯坦打破了停战协议
Aethelstan has taken an axe to the truce.
你从中调停的协议
A truce you brokered.
他蹂躏了低地村庄…
What he has done in the villages of the lowlands--
有他在爱尔兰凶残吗？
-Is it worse than his cruelty in Irland? -Tales to spread fear.
-那是为了散播恐惧的谣言 -我们被迫迎战
We had no choice but to defend ourselves.
这并非我们所愿
We did not start this.
-你们怎么找到我的？间谍是谁？ -我们有很多间谍，掌握了很多情报
-How did you find me? Who's your spy? -We have many spies. We know many things.
我们知道你被艾索斯坦放逐了
We know Aethelstan has banished you.
我们也知道他喜欢被人骑
And we know he gets humped like a woman.
也许这对你们异教徒没什么
That may be customary to you pagans,
但我们基督徒绝不容许
but as a Christian, it cannot be endured.
-我听说他可享受了 -那么…
-He endures it often, from what I hear. -So…
既然你跟我们有共同的敌人
As a man who shares our enemy,
跟我们结盟吧，乌特雷德
we ask you to join with us, Uhtred, in our alliance.
一起对抗暴君
Stand against the tyrant.
我已经厌倦战争了
I'm heartsick of battles.
你不是战士吗？你不想去英灵殿了？
What has become of the warrior? Do you no longer yearn for Valhalla?
乌特雷德，你知道预言吗？
Do you know the prophecy, Uhtred?
我们族人有个古老预言
The ancient prophecy of my people?
全不列颠将联合起来对抗萨克逊人
All of Britain will unite against the Saxons,
把他们推入肯特海
push them into the Kentish sea,
重新效忠亚瑟王的血脉
return the feals to the line of Arthur.
没错
There.
耆老的预言
The vision of an old man.
-绝对不会错 -我们诺桑比亚也有个预言
-So it must be true. -We Northumbrians also have a prophecy.
“七王丧钟”
"Seven kings must die."
没什么好怕的
That holds no fear.
在场每个人都有继承人
Each man here has a son to take his place.
七位国王
Seven kings die,
逝去的同时 也有七位国王崛起
seven will, in that moment, be made.
没错
It's true.
只要有子嗣，王国就能延续到下一代
If you make a child, your kingdom stands beyond you.
饱受战争蹂躏的王国
A kingdom ravaged by war, yes.
还有一个可能的
Then there is another way
办法
to consider.
如果真要避免血战
If you wish to save many from bloodshed.
只杀一个人
Kill one man only.
杀了攻打所有人的国王
Kill the king who has attacked us all.
回去请求他的饶恕
Return to him in… supplication.
伺机而动
Seize the moment.
只要夺走一条生命，就能拯救众生
Save many lives by simply taking one.
否则就是开战
The alternative, of course, is war.
七王对一王
Seven kings against one.
如果艾索斯坦想团结不列颠的部落
If Aethelstan wanted to unite the tribes of Britain,
那他已经成功了
he has succeeded.
你来做什么？
Why do you seek us here?
你的任务是让温彻斯特火力全开
Your part is to keep Winchester aroused.
你为什么放走乌特雷德？
You let Uhtred go free. Why?
我给了他任务
I sent him away.
去杀死你的国王朋友
To kill your friend, the king.
他会先没命的
-Well, he will be killed in the attempt.
乌特雷德比你高明多了
Uhtred has skills you do not.
不管是他攻击艾索斯坦 还是艾索斯坦攻击他
He attacks Aethelstan. Aethelstan attacks him.
都无所谓
It barely matters.
总之开战时，对手将士气低落
Either way, we face in battle men whose spirits have been broken.
英格曼德，你去西边，时候快到了
Ingilmundr, go to the West. The time is near.
亚丝翠，盯紧我们在诺桑比亚的朋友
Astrid, watch our friends in Northumbria.
（温彻斯特）
（威塞克斯王国，温彻斯特）
没想到又见面了
I did not think I would see you again.
陛下
Lord King.
我要为我儿请求你的宽恕
In the name of my son, I beg forgiveness.
饶了他吧
Spare him.
我愿向你称臣
Let me kneel to you.
那我会撤除你的放逐令
Then I lift your banishment.
给我一把剑，都出去吧
Give me a sword and then leave us.
来吧
Go on, then.
宣誓吧
Do it.
我以吾儿性命发誓
I swear this on my son's life.
誓词如下
Hear this as an oath.
英格曼德是间谍
Ingilmundr is a spy.
他和安拉夫联合大不列颠所有国王 打算推翻你
He's working with Anlaf to ally British kings against you.
-你说谎 -是真的，我在昔得兰见到他
-Lies. -It is true. I saw him in Shetland.
他派安拉夫的战士来找我 企图说服我反叛…
He told Anlaf's warriors to track me. They tried to turn me--
不可能！
No!
-他跟你儿子在塞沃尔！ -他泄露了你的事情
-He is in Thelwael with your son! -He told them things of you.
他还是信奉众神
He still follows my gods.
你暂时还有优势
For now, you have an advantage.
英格曼德不知道自己曝光了
Ingilmundr does not know he has been discovered.
他不可能背叛我
No, he would not betray me.
我才背叛了他
If anything, I have betrayed him.
-不 -他是上帝的信徒，而我是罪人！
-No. -He is a man of God, and I am a sinner!
这是他灌输你的，为了让你发起战争
He has convinced you of this to provoke your campaign.
-为了团结你的敌人 -不可能
-To unite your enemies. -No!
艾索斯坦，醒醒吧 他们已经结成巨大的联盟
Aethelstan, please see this. This alliance he has gathered is too large.
-准备来占领你的土地 -不！你说谎！
-Your lands will be overrun. -No! You lie!
全是谎言！
This is all lies!
艾索斯坦，请你听我说
Aethelstan, please hear me.
我为什么要骗你？
Why would I lie to you?
-出去 -艾索斯坦
-Get out. -Aethelstan--
滚，我不想看到你，守卫！
Get out. Get from my sight! Guards!
把他带走
-Take him!
王八蛋，给我滚
You dog! On your way.
我们搜遍了森林山谷
We search every forest, every valley.
结果他就在繁华的城市
And here he is, back in the lap of luxury.
听说你需要我们
We heard you needed us.
众神太眷顾我了 给我这么好的朋友
Truly the gods smiled at me to give me such friends.
我们找间酒馆
Let's find ourselves an alehouse,
好好想个对策
make a plan.
-谁告诉你们我在这里？ -她说你需要我们
-Who told you I was here? - She said you called for us.
你没派人传话吗？
-Did you not send for us, Lord? -She said you needed us.
她说你需要护卫
And requested a guard.
一个丹麦女生，艾索斯坦的宫女
Danish girl, serves in Aethelstan's court.
费南，我没有派人传话
Finan, I sent no word.
也没有要你们离开贝班堡
No command for you to leave Bebbanburg.
-你们在这看守城门 -是，大人
- Stay here and guard the gates. - Yes, Lord.
狼战士
Wolf-Warriors.
是安拉夫干的好事
This is Anlaf's doing.
英格丽丝！
Ingrith!
大人，大家都去哪了？
Lord, where are they all?
-艾格芙 -乌特雷德
- Eadgifu? -Uhtred.
怎么回事？
What happened?
我们听说这里遭受攻击，状况惨烈
When news reached us of the attack and torture here,
院长便派我们来协助伤者
the abbess sent us to help the injured.
可是我们无法接近他们
But we cannot get to the injured.
她在哪里？我妻子呢？
Where… Where is she? Where's my wife?
“七王丧钟”，大人
"Seven kings must die," Lord.
“七位国王”
"Seven kings
“和你心爱的女人”
and the woman you love."
英格丽丝！
Ingrith!
-英格丽丝 -全部都来帮忙
-No. Ingrith! -Every man is to help move it.
你，去上面
You, up above.
-有人听见吗？ -提防安拉夫的手下
- Can anyone hear me? - Watch for signs of Anlaf's men.
我们无能为力，只能安抚他们
We tried to help, but all we could do was comfort them.
乌特雷德，英格丽丝说 他们威胁还会回来
Uhtred, Ingrith said they threatened to return.
-我们必须保护自己 -先救出里面的人再说
-We must secure ourselves. -Not until we rescue those within.
你们上一次说话是什么时候？
When did you speak last?
大约三天前
About three days ago.
接住绳子
- Get the rope up there!
加油
Come on!
用力拉
Pull!
拉
用力拉！
Pull!
出力
用力拉！
Now!
费南
Finan.
她在哪里？
Where is…
不要啊！
No!
是我害死他们的
I brought this on them.
这一切都是安拉夫造成的
What they suffered is on Anlaf's account.
你不能被打败
You cannot let this break you.
我们已残破不堪
We are broken.
我们没有盟友，没有希望
We have no allies. We're lost.
我们必须勇敢保卫诺桑比亚 抵御他们再次入侵
Then we must find the courage to defend Northumbria from their return.
只要成功困住他们
If we endure and keep them at siege,
英格兰各地就有时间备战
we will give those in other parts of England time to prepare.
我们的牺牲
Whatever we suffer
能保护远方的人
protects those we are apart from.
她说得对，大人
She's right, Lord.
奥斯柏可以渡过爱尔兰海…
Osbert can cross the Irish Sea, get to--
爱尔兰海？
The Irish Sea?
我们得快马加鞭 安拉夫想让这里成为众矢之的
We must find the fastest horses. I think Anlaf is hoping to turn all eyes here.
他要引诱艾索斯坦
To lure Aethelstan.
他们会在自己的地盘登陆
But they will land where they have men.
英格曼德掌管威勒尔的驻军
Ingilmundr holds a garrison in the Wirral.
我们的儿子也在那里
With… With our sons.
（塞沃尔）
（威勒尔半岛）
要出事了
Something's underway.
我准备好了
I'm ready.
保重
Take care.
快进去
Get in the cart.
你们看看脖子上的刀，好好想清楚
Those of you with swords to your throats face a decision.
一千艘船正驶向这里
A thousand ships are heading towards these shores.
有些已经上岸了
Some have already landed.
要不了一周 我们就会占领所有萨克逊市镇
Within a week, Saxon boroughs will be overrun.
加入我们，一起推翻暴君艾索斯坦
Join us and fight the tyrant Aethelstan,
否则就去死吧
or die.
为爱德华国王…
For King Ed--
-别乱动  -这边走
- Keep still. - This way!
是的，先生。我相信是的。
Yes, sir. I believe so.
我们有看见，但他们走了
We saw them, but they got away.
-在很远的地方 -谢谢
-There. Far away. -Thank you.
不客气
Yes, my lord.
没有塞沃尔的消息，大人
No word from Thelwael, Lord.
我知道全都告诉他们了。
Told them all I knew.
希崔里克
Sihtric.
是
Lord?
我们终于要面对失败了吗？
Do we finally face defeat?
我所认识的战将
All the warrior kings that I've known,
厄柏、肯努特、血发
Ubba, Cnut, Bloodhair,
他们最终都失败了，还牵连众多生命
all have faced defeat in the end and have taken others with them.
大人，战争永远不会停
The fight was always coming, Lord.
死得轰轰烈烈才是勇士
No warrior dies a peaceful death.
她早就预见了，“七王丧钟”
She saw it all. "Seven kings must die."
我们还有希望
We have hope.
你从来没有称王的打算
In your heart, you never wanted to be a king.
有打听到我儿子的消息吗？
Have those fleeing heard anything of my son?
在得到确定的消息前
Then until I know for sure,
他都还活着
he is alive.
如果征战顺利 也许安拉夫会满足于麦西亚
And if conquest is easy, perhaps Anlaf may be satisfied with Mercia.
-那里土壤肥… -他不会满足的
-It is fertile-- - He will not be satisfied.
他们是为了 熄灭英格兰统一的梦想而来
They come Viking now to extinguish an idea of England.
这个梦想将团结往日的敌人
A dream unites a people who once sought to kill each other.
一旦熄灭，我们将重回黑暗时代
Without it, we go back into an age of darkness.
我们都失去了太多
We have both lost so much.
但我问自己
But I ask myself…
我还活着吗？
am I alive?
你能感觉到吗？
Can you feel it?
你还活着
You are alive.
你也是
So are you.
我们还有希望
So we have hope.
艾德蒙？
Edmund?
奥斯柏？
Osbert?
艾德蒙？
Edmund?
我来找英格曼德
I came seeking Ingilmundr.
为了证明你说谎
To prove that you had lied to me.
但你没骗我
But you had not.
我们是来找儿子的
We came to search for our sons.
带奥斯柏和艾德蒙出来
Bring out Osbert and Edmund.
奥斯柏
Osbert!
他们躲藏起来，逃过了大屠杀
They hid themselves and were spared the massacre.
陛下
Lord King,
大恩大德，没齿难忘
you have my endless gratitude.
过去这一年，我完全变了个人
I've not been myself this past year, and truly,
真的，我...
truly, I…
现在终于付出代价
I pay for my sins.
布鲁南博尔集结了大批联军
I face a great alliance at Brunanburh.
后悔没有意义
All regret is worthless.
好好策划如何迎战吧
Let us speak only of the fight to come.
-奥斯柏，你听到什么消息？ -他们在高地扎营
-Osbert, what have you learnt? -They've set up camp on high ground.
有六支军队
And they have six armies.
七支军队将在布鲁南博尔交战
Then seven armies shall meet at Brunanburh.
我不要你参战，乌特雷德
I do not want you to fight for me, Uhtred.
-我是支持你的… -我知道
- Trust I'm on your side-- -I know that.
去逃命吧
Save yourself.
带你儿子去安全之处
Take your son to safety.
要是我战死沙场，还有人能继位
If I do not survive the battle, then succession will be secure.
你无法独自击退联军
You cannot fight this alliance alone.
我禁止你参战
Yet I forbid you from taking part.
把带他走，皮尔里各神父 全部都带走
Take him, Father Pyrlig. Please, take them all.
-这一切是我造成的 -让我们效力吧
-I've dragged you all to this fate. - Let us serve you.
艾索斯坦
Aethelstan…
这不是对你的惩罚
this is not a punishment.
我想我们都心知肚明
I think we both know that it is.
这是以身殉难
This is martyrdom.
他以寡击众，必死无疑
He will not survive so great a number.
我们才得到赦免
But we have been reprieved.
-上帝要我们前往安全之处 -我不信上帝
-God is telling us to get to safety. -Your god does not speak to me.
避开必败之战并非懦弱之举
It is not cowardly to spurn a battle that cannot be won.
就是
It is.
无论如何，我逃跑是不争的事实
However this prevails, I will have to know I walked away from danger.
你也会有属于你的战争
Your battles will come
等你当上国王之后
when you become king.
母后，哪里的国王？
King of where, Mother?
我们要参战
-We will fight with the shield wall.
-不 -奥斯柏
-No. -Osbert,
-你准备好了吗？ -就等你这句话
-are you ready? -I've always been ready.
皮尔里各 你曾说拯救英格兰是我的天命
Pyrlig, you once told me that it was my destiny to save England.
但不是这个样子
Hadn't seen it quite like this,
算了，反正我也不信预言
but then I'm not one for prophecies.
如果你的天命是保护艾德蒙呢？
What if your destiny is to protect Edmund?
也许他才能统一英格兰 他才是伟大的国王
Perhaps he is the one to unite England. He could be the king who was worthy.
没有国王能统一英格兰
No king will form England.
这就是我现在看到的
This is what I see now.
艾德蒙、爱德华、艾佛雷德 甚至艾索斯坦都不可能
Not Edmund or Edward or Alfred. Not even Aethelstan.
艾佛雷德的梦想是团结人民
Alfred's dream was of a united people.
为此我和这群来自各地的人奋斗至今
And with these men, from all parts, I fought for it.
如果我们的天命不是统一英格兰
What if our destiny was not to form England,
而是团结英格兰人民呢？
but to form the English as one force?
谁比半个撒克逊人和半个丹麦人 更适合领导四分五裂的人民？我们走
Who better than a half Saxon, half Dane to lead men from divided places? We go!
我应该不必称自己英格兰人吧？
I don't have to call myself English, do I?
（布鲁南博尔）
（威勒尔半岛，布鲁南博尔）
庆祝成这样，好像已经胜利似的
To hear that, you'd think they'd won already.
我们应该前进
We should make our way.
如果要赢，就得加入前线
If this is to work, we need to be on the front line.
-攻击敌人的左侧 -为什么？
-We'll aim for their left side. -Why?
为什么是左侧？
Why the left?
较没防备，人们大多用右手挥剑
Weaker. Most men fight with the sword in their right hand.
我跟乌特雷德征战多次，相信他吧
I've fought with Uhtred many times. Trust he will find a way.
你
You.
这把剑哪来的？
Where did you find that?
我在艾尔斯伯里用五枚硬币买来的
I bought it in Aegelesburg for five pieces.
能借看吗？
May I?
我用这把跟你交换
I will exchange it for this one.
这更值钱，上面还有石榴石
It is worth much more, and it has a garnet.
别讨价还价 那把剑归你，这把剑归我
When I say exchange, I mean you take that one, and I keep this one.
我不是你们的指挥官，也不是将领
I am no commander of yours.
只是身经百战的战士
I have no authority other than being a man who has fought in many battles.
有些人曾在我的麾下
Some of you I have led before.
今天，我以士兵的身分 与各位并肩作战
Today I stand with you as a simple soldier.
我请求各位 再次在战场上
But I ask that, on the field,
接受我的指引
you once again let me guide you.
我们在山丘上，处于弱势
Our position on the hill is weak,
但左侧的树林有敌人看不见的优势
but the trees to our left give us an advantage the enemy will not see.
只要我们团结一心
We can defeat them
必能战胜
if we stay united.
-我的酒都醒了 -狐臭薰天
-This is one way to clear the ale. -Smell of a thousand armpits.
搞不好他们一闻就跑了
Aye. Maybe they smelled us and ran away.
-也许吧 -谁摸我屁股？
- Maybe. - Who touched my arse?
天啊
Oh my God!
我的天
Jesus!
千军万马
Rather a lot of them, isn't there?
乌特雷德？
Uhtred?
乌特雷德
Uhtred.
-我们要怎么办？ -看到那些袋子了吗？
-How do we face this? -You see these bags?
传给前线的人，快
Give them to the men on the front line. Go.
听到口令再举盾牌
Do not raise your shield until you have to.
放轻松，别紧张
Stay at ease. Stay relaxed.
别露出不安的表情
And do not show them we are unsettled.
大人，他来了
Lord! He's here.
暴君来了
Here he comes. The tyrant himself.
好了吗？
Is it done?
-退得越远越好 -是
-Get back as far as you can. -Yeah.
组成盾墙！
Shield wall!
（布鲁南博尔之战）
（西元937年）
-准备好了吗，混球们？ -来吧
-Are we ready, arselings? - Yeah!
大家都告解完了
I have taken their confessions.
待会我叫你们往后退
When I ask you to give ground,
就往后退
do it.
只要退到树林后，就是时候了
When you see the trees in front of you, it will be time.
你有信心吗？
Do you think this will work?
要是不成功，我们也不会知道
If it does not, we will not be here to see it.
相信我
Trust me.
听我指令
And follow.
组成盾墙！
Shield wall!
组成
Shield!
盾墙！
Wall!
往后退！
Step back!
后退！
Back!
他们在撤退？
They retreat?
我们根本还没出手
Even before we engage?
-往后退 -他们知道自己已经输了
-Step back! - They know they have lost already.
让我们杀个痛快
Let's enjoy it.
前进！
- Forward!
我以纯净的心侍奉上帝，我要感谢祂
I thank God, who I serve with pure conscience.
上帝赐予我们勇气、力量
God hath not given us a spirit of fear, but of power…
爱
…love…
健全的心灵
…and of sound mind!
阿门
Amen.
往后退！
Step back!
预备！
Brace!
重整阵形！冲锋！
Re-form! Charge!
萨克逊混帐！
Saxon bastards!
皮尔里各！
Pyrlig!
不！
No!
皮尔里各
Pyrlig!
你们两步，你们一步，听我口令！
-Two paces! One pace! -Mm-hmm.
祈祷会成功吧
-On my command! - Let's hope this works!
退后两步！
Two paces back!
退后！
Back!
Step back!
退后一步！
One pace back!
他们退缩了，我们占上风
They back off. We have them.
-找出国王！
-Find the king! - Find the king!
后退！
Step back!
往后退！
Go backwards!
为昔得兰而战！
For Shetland!
为奥克尼而战！
For Orkney!
往后
Step back!
-继续退！
-Keep going!
后退！
Back!
保持阵形！
Protect the line! Protect the line!
退后！
Step back!
再往后退我们就要被占领了
They'll overrun us if we keep giving ground!
侧翼在搞什么？
What are they doing along the flank?
传话出去，艾索斯坦就在我们前面
Send a message that Aethelstan is in front of us!
往后退！
Step back!
退后！
大人，阵形正在改变
The line's turning, Lord. We're coming around!
大人，艾索斯坦在苏格兰前线
Aethelstan is on the Scots' line, Lord.
野猪阵
Swine wedge!
往后退！
Step back!
野猪阵！
Swine wedge!
安拉夫，住手！
Anlaf! Stop!
前进！
Push forward!
他们要抓艾索斯坦！
They're going for Aethelstan!
往后！
Step back!
后退！
Back!
盾墙撑不住了！
The wall will not hold!
艾索斯坦，保持阵形！
Aethelstan, hold the line!
还要多久，大人？快了
- How much longer, Lord? - We're almost there.
他们要攻破艾索斯坦的阵形了
They're breaking through Aethelstan's line, Lord!
我们撑不住了
We can't hold!
后退！
Step back!
前进！
Push forward!
大人
Lord!
Lord.
保护国王！
Protect the king!
艾索斯坦
Aethelstan!
大人，树林！
Lord, trees!
阵形完成了，大人
We've turned them, Lord! We've turned the line.
-发出信号 -是，大人
- Give the signal! - Yes, Lord.
-不太对劲 -阵形变换了
-Something's not right. - We've been turned around!
让开
Make way! Make way!
乌特雷德大人下令了
Lord Uhtred orders the signal.
攻击！
Attack!
小心后面！
Behind!
去抓国王！
Hunt down their kings!
这是陷阱！
It's a trap!
我的儿子
My son!
不！
No!
防守！
Guards!
撤退！
Fall back! Fall back!
苏格兰军撤退！
Scots! Fall back!
Hyah!
艾索斯坦
Aethelstan!
艾索斯坦！
皮尔里各？
Pyrlig?
那天，五位国王落荒而逃
Five kings escaped the field that day,
他们的儿子
but their sons,
则战死沙场 包括奥克尼、曼岛、昔得兰
Orkney, Man, Shetland,
斯特拉斯克莱德和苏格兰
Strathclyde, and Scotland, did not.
这里每个人
Each man here
都丢下了一位继承人！
has left behind an heir.
稍安勿躁
We wait.
我们要趁他们撤离时进攻 救回亲人的尸体
Then attack those leaving the field and return for our kin.
别傻了，安拉夫
Do not be any more foolish, Anlaf.
昔得兰？
Shetland?
我们不去送死
No more death.
奥克尼，我们必须战斗！
Orkney, we need to fight!
还有什么意义吗？
What is there to fight for?
我需要一艘船回爱尔兰
I need a ship to get back to Irland.
你呢？
You?
大人！
Lord!
乌特雷德！
Uhtred!
乌特雷德
嘿，嘿，你。
Hey. Hey, you.
费南
Finan! Finan!
（这场战役是该岛史上 往生者人数最多的一次）
（剑伤占死因之首）
（《盎格鲁萨克逊编年史》）
你曾付出真心吗？
Was any of it real?
告诉我实话
Tell me the truth.
告解完了再去见上帝吧
When you find yourself before God, you will have confessed.
我的确喜欢上你
I grew fond of you.
-但我更爱我的族人 -我为了你背叛了自己人
-But my love for my people prevailed. -I chose you over my people.
也许我的众神比你的上帝更强大
Perhaps my gods are stronger than yours.
那为什么是我活着？
Then why am I living…
你却面临死亡？
and you about to die?
命运深不可测
Only fools try to understand destiny.
乌特雷德
Uhtred.
-我儿子还活着吗？
Did my son survive?
-是的
Yes.
贝班堡又是我们的了
And Bebbanburg is ours again.
-我们要用石头重建贝班堡 -未来充满希望
-We will rebuild in stone. - There is so much future.
撑下去，乌特雷德
Stay with us, Uhtred.
-敌人呢？ -我们打赢了
-What of the enemy? - The victory is ours.
五名国王之子战死沙场
Five sons of kings lay dead upon the battlefield.
-五位无冕国王 -“七王丧钟”
-Five kings that will never be crowned. - "Seven kings must die."
预言错了，大人
The prophecy was wrong, Lord.
加上威塞克斯的爱德华国王 就是六王了
With Edward of Wessex, it makes six.
我是第七个吗？
Am I to be the seventh?
我已经吩咐编年史家记录你的胜利 乌特雷德
I have told the chroniclers to write of your victory, Uhtred.
我不想被写进你们的历史
I have no wish to be written into your history.
我只想因为信守誓言而进入英灵殿
I want only to be honored in the feast hall for standing by an oath.
乌特雷德，你不只是支持我
Uhtred, you did not just stand by me.
还为了我而战
You stood for me.
你办到了我所办不到的
You led where I could not.
你原谅了我
And you forgave me
即使我罪该万死
when I was unforgivable.
你守护了英格兰的希望
You saved the hope of England.
它一定会在未来实现
Now in time, it may yet happen.
我曾经说过
I said that…
如果你能证明自己是合法的国王
if you proved yourself to be the rightful king,
我就会向你称臣
I would swear Northumbria to you.
许多人为了英格兰战死沙场
Men have died fighting under the name of the English.
为了纪念他们，英格兰应该统一
To honor them, England should be formed.
但我有一个条件
But I have one condition.
你必须宣誓永不结婚
You must make an oath never to marry.
永不生子
No heirs.
让你弟弟艾德蒙能顺利继承王位
So your brother Edmund can take the throne unchallenged.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我向你发誓
This oath I shall swear.
那我们将称臣于你
Then we submit to you as our king.
你将成为威塞克斯、麦西亚
Which makes you ruler of Wessex, Mercia, East Anglia,
东盎格利亚和诺桑比亚的统治者
and Northumbria.
我的领土叫做
And I call my lands
英格兰
England.
国王万岁
Long live the king!
Long live the king.
英格兰国王万岁
Long live the King of England.
回房休息吧，大人
Return to your chamber, Lord.
别为我难过
Do not grieve for me.
我的天命是战死沙场
It was always written that I would fall in battle.
你不会死的，大人
You're not gonna die, Lord.
我就逃过死劫，所以…
-I would go first, and I'm still alive…
对
So,
天命不可违
destiny is all.
七王死了吗？
Did seven kings die?
编年史并未记录乌特雷德大人的生死
The chronicles do not record if my lord Uhtred survived.
但所有认识他的人
But those like me, who knew him,
都视他为这个时代最伟大的战士
recognize him as the greatest warrior of our age,
以及建国功臣
and a man who made a kingdom.
（艾索斯坦统治了15年）
（他被公认为中世纪英格兰 第一位且最伟大的国王）
（丹麦人持续入侵英格兰）
（直到1066年 被自己的诺曼后裔征服为止）
（贝班堡的堡垒耸立至今）
（贝班堡）
（诺森伯兰郡班伯城堡，现今）